Updated: 06/02/2024

# **Bernard Spiegl**

Helsinki, Finland



I am an enthusiastic, curious and adept engineer with an interdisciplinary background, currently working at the intersection of deep learning and neuroscience. My current research revolves around development of diffusion-based deep generative modelling approach for solving neuroscience-inspired problem; novel view synthesis. To this end, my research revolves around the development of new tools and solutions by intertwining both domain-specific and interdisciplinary knowledge.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Master of Science - Signal Processing and Data Science with honours | Aalto University with minors in Human Neuroscience and Technology; Acoustics and Audio Technology

2021 - 2023

- MSc thesis: ViewFusion Learning Composable Diffusion Models for Novel View Synthesis; jointly supervised by Prof. Alexander Ilin and Prof. Stéphane Deny arXiv preprint [PDF], press release [link]
- focus areas: Computer Vision, Neuroscience, Speech and Language Processing

# **Bachelor of Science - Computer Science** | University of Zagreb

2018 - 2021

- BSc thesis: Contrastive Unpaired Translation using Focal Loss for Patch Classification;
   supervised by Prof. Siniša Šegvić arXiv preprint [PDF]
- · focus areas: Computer Vision, Deep Learning

### **EXPERIENCE**

# Project Employee | Aalto University | Helsinki, Finland

OCT 2023 — PRESENT

• Expanding on my master's thesis research as a part of Prof. Stéphane Deny's BRAIN lab.

#### Teaching Assistant | Aalto University | Helsinki, Finland

2023; 2024

- CS-E4890 Deep Learning course, Prof. Alexander Ilin.
- Coordinated weekly in-person and remote TA sessions for over 400 enrolled students.
- Introduced experimental flipped classroom paper reading sessions for enthusiastic students.

#### Research Assistant | Aalto University | Helsinki, Finland

**APR 2022 — JUN 2022** 

- Implemented a deep neural network architecture that combines VQ-VAE to compress the audio and an autoregressive transformer producing latent responses, in an endeavor to simulate musical call and response interaction.
- Part of a research project on usage of AI in music and creative processes coordinated by Koray Tahiroğlu in collaboration with Google Brain (Magenta Team).

# Data Scientist Intern | RealNetworks Inc. | Zagreb, Croatia

JUL 2021 — AUG 2021

• Researched and tested deep learning architectures (CNNs, transformers, etc.) for speech classification in order to enable real-time robocall detection for the US market.

Software Engineering Intern | Koncar – Electrical Industry Inc. | Zagreb, Croatia

JUL 2019; JUL 2020 — AUG 2020

- Developed a GUI client for real-time network communication via Modbus protocol.
- Developed a real-time communication and data management web application for SCADA based wind turbine systems.

# **Undergraduate Teaching Assistant** | University of Zagreb | Zagreb, Croatia

FEB 2019 — JUL 2019

· Assisted students during laboratory exercises in Fundamentals of Electrical Engineering.

### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

| HIIT Funding                 | Received funding from Helsinki Institute for Information Technology for my master's | 2023 |
|------------------------------|---|------|
|                              | thesis research.  |      |
| Dean's Incentive Scholarship | Received a scholarship awarded by Aalto University for good academic progress.      | 2022 |
| Google Foobar                | Received an invitation to Google's Foobar secret coding challenge.                  | 2022 |
| STEM Scholarship             | Received a scholarship for being among the top students on matriculation exam in    | 2018 |
|                              | fields of Mathematics and Physics.  |      |

#### **LEADERSHIP**

#### Head of Maintenance & Skipper | Teekkaripurjehtijat ry | Helsinki, Finland

2023 - 2024

• Managing a sustainable electric sailboat refurbishment project valued at over 20,000€ in a student sailing club. Secured 4,500€ in external project funding thus far.

## **Ambassador** | United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime | Vienna, Austria

**MAR 2018** 

• Represented Croatia at an international youth forum, organised by the UNODC in the margins of 61st session of the Commission on Narcotic Drugs, delivering a statement to the policy making body and giving an interview [link].

## SKILLS AND INTERESTS

| Languages              | Fully proficient in Python (NumPy, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Pandas, matplotlib, scikit-learn, asyncio); |
|------------------------|---|
|                        | intermediate in C/C++, SQL, R, MATLAB, Java, bash; working knowledge of web stack (JS, HTML, CSS)   |
| Technologies           | Git, Slurm, Cluster Computing (Distributed Training, Dataset Sharding, etc.)                        |
| Professional Interests | Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Neuroscience  |

Professional Interests
Personal Interests

Sailing, Music Production and Sound Design, Guitar and Piano Playing

Natural Languages Croatian (native), English (fluent - C2 (TOEFL iBT 114/120)), German (limited), Italian (limited), Finnish

(basic)